A Guide to the Virginia Dept. of Public Welfare Minute Books, 1900-1942
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Dept. of Public Welfare Minute Books, 1900-1942
Library of Virginia
36234
13 v.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Dept. of Welfare and Institutions, Jan. 15, 1965.
Biographical/Historical Information
Although the Virginia State Penitentiary was built in Richmond in 1797, a statewide penal system was not developed until over a century later. An act passed by the General Assembly on March 13, 1908, created the Board of Charities and Corrections to administer the penitentiary and several penal farms. On February 27, 1922, the General Assembly passed an act that created the Board of Public Welfare and merged the Board of Charities and Corrections with it. The state government reorganization act passed on April 18, 1927, created the Department of Public Welfare to administer the prison system. Legislation approved March 13, 1942, created both the Department of Corrections and the Parole Board as independent agencies. Corrections departments were merged into the Department of Welfare and Institutions by a government reorganization act approved by the General Assembly on March 30, 1948. This department remained intact until March 9, 1974, when the General Assembly passed an act dividing it into the Department of Welfare, now the Department of Social Services and the Department of Corrections. Three major responsibilities were given to the Department of Corrections: youth, adult services, and probation and parole services.
Scope and Content Information
Minute books and reports of the the various boards and committees concerned with juvenile offenders in Virginia. Included are Virginia Industrial School for Boys, Virginia Home and Industrial School for Girls, Virginia Manual Labor School for Colored Boys, Negro Reformatory Association of Virginia, and the Prison Association of Virginia.
Contents List
- Minute books, 1900-1942
  - Virginia Industrial School for Boys (Beaumont School for Boys), Board of Directors, Minutes, 1929 Jan 3-1933 Jul 18 (Box AA)
  - Virginia Industrial School for Boys (Beaumont School for Boys), Board of Directors, Minutes, 1939 Feb 8-1940 Nov 25 (Box AA)
  - Virginia Home and Industrial School for Girls (Bon Air Learning Center), Board of Directors, Minutes, 1940 Nov 30-1941 Dec 4 (Box AA)
  - Reports of Superintendents, 1931 Apr 6-1936 Dec 31 (Box AA)
  - Reports of Superintendents, 1937 Jan 31-1941 Oct 1 (Box AA)
  - Negro Reformatory Association of Virginia, Board of Trustees, Minutes, 1905 Nov 24-1939 May 10 (Box BB)
  - Negro Reformatory Association of Virginia, Board of Trustees, Minutes, 1939 Aug 9-1942 Jun 24 (Box BB)
  - Virginia Home and Industrial School for Girls (Bon Air Learning Center), Board of Directors, Minutes, 1933 Jan 3-1942 Jun 4 (Box CC)
  - Virginia Industrial School for Boys (Beaumont School for Boys), Executive Committee, Minutes, 1925 Mar 3-1933 Oct 2 (Box CC)
  - Virginia Industrial School for Boys (Beaumont School for Boys), Executive Committee, Minutes, 1933 Oct 2-1942 Jun 30 (Box CC)
  - Virginia Manual Labor School for Colored Boys (Hanover School for Boys), Executive Committee, Minutes, 1922 May 5-1940 Feb 21 (Box CC)
  - Virginia Industrial School for Boys (Beaumont School for Boys), Board of Directors, Minutes, 1920 Jun 14-1928 Dec 6 (Box DD)
  - Prison Association of Virginia, Board of Directors, Minutes, 1900 May 22-1908 Mar 17 (Box DD)
  - Prison Association of Virginia, Board of Directors, Minutes, 1908 Apr 21-1916 Oct 17 (Box DD)